<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "User_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter id="chap-services">
	<title>Services</title>

	<section>
		<title>Building XATMI services and clients</title>
		<para>This article should explain how to work with the Blacktie
			framework in order to develop your own XATMI services and clients. We
			will discuss how to run the code generation tool along with how to
			provide the configuration files that are required on the client and
			server side.</para>



		<section>
			<title>Pre-requisites</title>

			<para>The provided
				&lt;BLACKTIE_BIN_DIR&gt;/setenv.[sh|bat] should be
				executed to put the build
				tools in the environment.</para>

			<section>
				<title>WINDOWS ONLY</title>

				<para>Install Visual V++ 2008 Express Edition (only used to provide
					the
					compiler
					and linker on Windows)</para>

				<para>The PATH environment variable will need the runtime DLLs in it
				</para>

				<para>
					<literal>C:\Program Files\Microsoft Visual Studio
						9.0\VC\redist\Debug_NonRedist\x86\Microsoft.VC90.DebugCRT
					</literal>
				</para>

				<para>The PATH environment variable will also need the VC++ tools in
					it</para>
				<para>
					<literal>C:\Program Files\Microsoft Visual Studio
						9.0\VC\vcvarsall.bat</literal>
				</para>
			</section>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>Configuring the server, services and clients</title>

			<para>Each of the following configuration files must be present at
				runtime
				inorder for Blacktie servers or clients to operate correctly
			</para>

			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>btconfig.xml (this file although of the same structure, the
						content
						will be different for windows and for linux)</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>

			<para>The schemas that these files must validate against
				are in
				&lt;BLACKTIE_BIN_DIR&gt;/schemas/xsd, you can read more about
				providing
				configuration here.</para>
		</section>


		<section>
			<title>Running the code generation tool</title>
			<para>When building clients or servers using the provided ANT script
				you
				will need to make sure you have set the environment in the manner
				indicated in
				&lt;BLACKTIE_BIN_DIR&gt;/setenv.[sh|bat]</para>

			<para>An example run
				configuration for the code generation tool would
				then
				look like:</para>
			<para>
				<programlisting>&lt;BLACKTIE_BIN_DIR&gt;/bin/generate_server.&lt;sh|bat&gt;
			-Dserver.includes=BarService.c -Dservice.names=BAR</programlisting>
			</para>

			<para>
				<programlisting>&lt;BLACKTIE_BIN_DIR&gt;/bin/generate_client.&lt;sh|bat&gt;
			-Dclient.includes=client.c</programlisting>
			</para>
		</section>


		<section>
			<title>Running a generated server and client</title>

			<para>The following are the requirements to run the generated server
				and
				client:</para>
			<para>The LD_LIBRARY_PATH or PATH must be set to include the
				&lt;BLACKTIE_BIN_DIR&gt;/lib
				folder (done
				by setenv.[sh|bat]</para>
			<para>The commands must be executed from the
				directory relative to
				where the
				configuration files exist</para>

			<para>Assuming the
				pre-requisites are adhered to all that must be done
				is to
				execute</para>
			<para>
				<literal>server[.exe] -c [configuration_dir] -i [unique_id]
				</literal>
				and then
			</para>
			<para>
				<literal>client[.exe]</literal>
				(if the client is not in the location of the
				configuration files you
				need to set the environment variable
				<literal>BLACKTIE_CONFIGURATION_DIR</literal>
				.
			</para>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>XATMI Services and BlackTie</title>

		<para>Here a service is defined as a unit of business logic that
			implements
			the tpservice(SVCINFO) method as defined in the XATMI
			specification
			section 3.3.</para>



		<para>In BlackTie services are broadly categorised as either:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>Administrative</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>User defined</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<section>
			<title>Administrative Services</title>
			<para>Each server exposes a single XATMI service that is built into
				the server
				executable and is exposed for the lifespan of the server.
				It is not
				intended to be accessed directly by the programmer although
				this is
				possible, instead however the results of the service are
				typically
				aggregated by a central Java domain-level XATMI
				administrative
				service.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>C XATMI Per Server Service</title>

			<para>The name of the service is not user defined although can be
				predicted:</para>
			<para>
				<literal>&lt;SERVER_NAME&gt;_ADMIN_&lt;SERVER_ID&gt;</literal>
			</para>

			<note>
				<para>User defined services are not allowed to be configured with a
					name with _ADMIN in them</para>
			</note>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>Java XATMI Domain-wide Service</title>

			<para>The name of the service again is not
				user defined although can
				be
				predicted from the domain name:</para>

			<para>
				<literal>&lt;DOMAIN_NAME&gt;_ADMIN</literal>
			</para>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>User Defined Services</title>
			<para>All user defined service names must be
				declared
				within the
				constraints
				defined in the XATMI specification
				plus several
				constraints imposed
				by BlackTie:</para>

			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>Service names must be 128
						characters or
						less</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Servers may not contain overlapping service names,
						e.g. server
						1
						and
						server 2 cannot define service A</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Service names may
						not use the
						reserved keyword _ADMIN_ in their
						name</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>The service must be
						defined in
						the btconfig.xml</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>The service may optionally be customized
						in the btconfig.xml
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>The same function for the same service is expected at each
						server</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>tpadvertise and tpunadvertise operate on the local service
						state,
						they
						are not used to (un)advertise the service at a domain
						wide
						level</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>If a
						service is not thread safe, it is important to set the
						SIZE for the SERVICE in
						the
						btconfig.xml file to 1</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Decoupling XATMI services and clients using a queuing pattern
		</title>
		<section>
			<title>Introduction</title>
			<para>Starting from release blacktie-3_0_0 we have added two methods
				called
				btenqueue and btdequeue to simplify sending and receiving
				message. The
				M1 release supports transactional sends and the M2
				release will
				support ﻿transactional receives.</para>

			<para>This page will be updated soon to reflect the change.</para>



			<para>XATMI (http://www.opengroup.org/pubs/catalog/c506.htm) is a
				standard which
				specifies how to connect clients to services. A client
				is a program
				that requests services to be performed. A service is a
				program that
				performs a specific application function on behalf of
				clients. In
				XATMI there are two types of service:</para>
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>Request/response services receive a single request and
						produce
						at most a single
						response to the request. The request is the
						application data sent from
						the client to the service. The service
						processes the request and
						returns application data to the client by
						means of at most one
						response;</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Conversational services are invoked by means of a connection
						request from the
						client. Once the connection is established and the
						service invoked,
						the client and the service can exchange data in an
						application-specific manner until the service returns, whereupon
						the
						connection is logically terminated.</para>
				</listitem>
			</orderedlist>


			<para>However this model breaks down if there is no service currently
				running that
				can handle the client request. The latest release of
				BlackTie includes
				an enhancement (to XATMI) that facilitates the
				queuing of client
				requests such that the request can be processed at
				a
				later time when
				an appropriate service becomes available.</para>



			<para>In XATMI message payloads are obtained using the following
				call:
		</para>



			<para>
				<programlisting language="C++" role="C++">char * tpalloc(char *type, char *subtype, long size)</programlisting>
			</para>



			<para>To take advantage of the new BlackTie feature you will need to
				pass an
				extra parameter to the XATMI buffer allocation routine:
			</para>



			<para>
				<programlisting language="C++" role="C++">char* btalloc(msg_opts_t* ctrl, char* type, char* subtype, long size);</programlisting>
			</para>



			<para>The resulting buffer can be used to make service requests with
				the following restrictions:</para>

			<orderedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>the client must use the asynchronous request/response model,
						i.e. it must use tpacall.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>the client must not expect a response, i.e. it must set the
						TPNOREPLY flag.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>it must not have any outstanding transaction.</para>
				</listitem>
			</orderedlist>


			<para>[Currently we are using the extra parameter to control the
				priority of message delivery though we could, in the future, add
				other features to give the client more control over the mechanism].
			</para>



			<para>And that's it, now when the requested service is brought
				on-line
				the queued requests will be made available to its' service
				routine.
				The latest BlackTie release
				(http://www.jboss.org/blacktie/downloads.html) includes an quickstart
				showing this feature in action. Unpack the release and look at the
				REAME in the quickstarts/xatmi/queues directory.</para>


			<para>There are two BlackTie specific config requirements to ensure
				that requests are queued even when the target server is unavailable;
			</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>the SERVICE definition in btconfig.xml must set the
						"externally-managed-destination" attribute to true;</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>you must deploy a JMS queue named BTR_[service name] to the
						application server (the XML file containing this queue definition
						must end with the suffix -service.xml)</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>


			<para>Internally BlackTie uses JMS queues to connect services with
				clients. Normally when a server calls tpadvertise a queue is created
				and clients may then connect with the server via that queue.
				However,
				no such server is running in the scenario we are discussing
				and this
				is the reason the queue needs to be deployed before running
				the
				client.</para>



			<para>So, for example, if the service name is TestOne then deploy a
				queue called BTR_TestOne to the JBoss deploy directory using an XML
				file containing the following:</para>



			<para>
				<programlisting language="XML" role="XML"><xi:include
					href="extras/registering_a_queue.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
					parse="text" /></programlisting>
			</para>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>How to use topics
		</title>
		<para>Basically, topics are used to burst out messages to multiple XATMI services 
			that do not necessarily expect a reponse.</para>

		<para>If it helps, you might consider using topics for things like stock ticker 
			updates where the receiver is not required to notify the sender that they have 
			received the ticker.</para>


		<para>
			To config a SERVIECE use topics, you could set type to 'topic', for example:
		</para>

		<para>
			<programlisting language="XML" role="XML"><xi:include
					href="extras/use_topic.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
					parse="text" /></programlisting>
		</para>

		<note>
			<para>clients do not need to configure the list of services in their btconfig.xml, 
				they will need to try to connect to the queue first, then, the topic (unless 
				they have the destination is configured in their btconfig.xml).
			</para>
		</note>

		<note>
			<para>tpacalls to topics MUST have TPNOREPLY set. If the client tpacalls a topic 
				without TPNOREPLY we should fail the call. It also means tpcalls should fail too.
			</para>

			<para>
				And there is a intention that externally-managed-destination is set to true as 
				there are multiple receivers.
			</para>
		</note>

		<para>You can get more information about these in quickstarts/xatmi/topics.
		</para>
	</section>
</chapter>
