<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "ArjunaCore_Administration_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter>
  <title>ORB-specific Configurations</title>
  
  <section>
    <title>JacORB</title>
    <para>
      For JacORB to function correctly it needs a valid <filename>jacorb.properties</filename> or
      <filename>.jacorb_properties</filename> file in one of the following places, in searched order:
    </para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The classpath
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The home directory of the user running the JBoss Transaction Service.  The home directory is retrieved using
          <methodname>System.getProperty( “user.home” );</methodname>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The current directory
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The <filename>lib/</filename> directory of the JDK used to run your application.  This is retrieved using
          <methodname>System.getProperty(“java.home” );</methodname>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <note>
      <para>
        A template <filename>jacorb.properties</filename> file is located in the JacORB installation directory.
      </para>
    </note>
    <para>
      Within the JacORB properties file there are two important properties which must be tailored to suit your
      application.
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          jacorb.poa.thread_pool_max
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          jacorb.poa.thread_pool_min
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      These properties specify the minimum and maximum number of request processing threads that JacORB uses in its
      thread pool.  If no threads are available, may block until a thread becomes available..  For more information on
      configuring JacORB, refer to the JacORB documentation.
    </para>
    <important>
      <para>
        JacORB includes its own implementation of the classes defined in the <filename>CosTransactions.idl</filename>
        file. Unfortunately these are incompatible with the version shipped with JBossTS. Therefore, the JBossTS jar
        files absolutely must appear in the CLASSPATH before any JacORB jars.
      </para>
    </important>
    <para>
      When running the recovery manager, it should always uses the same well-known port for each machine on which it
      runs. Do not use the <varname>OAPort</varname> property provided by JacORB unless the recovery manager has its own
      <filename>jacorb.properties</filename> file or the property is provided on the command line when starting the
      recovery manager. If the recovery manager and other components of JBossTS share the same
      <filename>jacorb.properties</filename> file, use the <varname>JTSEnvironmentBean.recoveryManagerPort</varname> and
      <varname>JTSEnvironmentBean.recoveryManagerAddress</varname> properties.
    </para>
  </section>
</chapter>

