<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "Transactions_XTS_Administration_And_Development_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter>
  
  <title>Getting Started</title>

  <indexterm><primary>user transactions</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm><primary>business activities</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm><primary>context handlers</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm><primary>participants</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm><primary>service-side handlers</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm><primary>JAX-RPC</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm><primary>com.arjuna.mw.wst11</primary><secondary>XTS API</secondary></indexterm>


  <section>
    <title>Installing the XTS Service Archive into JBoss Transaction Service</title>
    <para>
      XTS, which is the Web Services component of JBoss Transaction Service, provides WS-AT and WS-BA support for Web
      Services hosted on the &APPSERVER;. The module is packaged as a <firstterm>Service Archive (.sar)</firstterm>
      located in <filename><replaceable>$JBOSS_HOME</replaceable>/docs/examples/transactions/</filename>. To install it,
      follow <xref linkend="procedure-install-xts" />.
    </para>

    <procedure id="procedure-install-xts">
      <title>Installing the XTS Module</title>
      <step>
   <para>
     Create a sub-directory in the
     <filename><replaceable>$JBOSS_HOME</replaceable>/server/[<replaceable>name</replaceable>]/deploy/</filename>
     directory, called <filename>jbossxts.sar/</filename>.
   </para>
      </step>
      <step>
   <para>
     Unpack the SAR, which is a ZIP archive, into this new directory.
   </para>
      </step>
      <step>
   <para>
     Restart &APPSERVER; to activate the module.
   </para>
      </step>
    </procedure>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Creating Client Applications</title>

    <para>
      There are two aspects to a client application using XTS, the transaction declaration aspects, and the business
      logic. The business logic includes the invocation of Web Services.
    </para>
    <para>
      Transaction declaration aspects are handled automatically with the XTS client API. This API provides simple
      transaction directives such as <methodname>begin</methodname>, <methodname>commit</methodname>, and
      <methodname>rollback</methodname>, which the client application can use to initialize, manage, and terminate
      transactions. Internally, this API uses SOAP to invoke operations on the various WS-C, WS-AT and WS-BA services,
      in order to create a coordinator and drive the transaction to completion.
    </para>

    <section>
      <title>User Transactions</title>
      <para>
   A client uses the <classname>UserTransactionFactory</classname> and <classname>UserTransaction</classname> classes to
   create and manage WS-AT transactions.  These classes provide a simple API which operates in a manner similar to the
   JTA API. A WS-AT transaction is started and associated with the client thread by calling the
   <methodname>begin</methodname> method of the <methodname>UserTransaction</methodname> class. The transaction can be
   committed by calling the <methodname>commit</methodname> method, and rolled back by calling the
   <methodname>rollback</methodname> method.
      </para>
      <para>
   More complex transaction management, such as suspension and resumption of transactions, is supported by the
   <classname>TransactionManagerFactory</classname> and <classname>TransactionManager</classname> classes.
      </para>
      <para>
   Full details of the WS-AT APIs are provided in <xref linkend="sec-xts-api" />.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Business Activities</title>

      <para>
   A client creates and manages Business Activities using the <classname>UserBusinessActivityFactory</classname> and
   <classname>UserBusinessActivity</classname> classes. A WS-BA activity is started and associated with the client
   thread by calling the <methodname>begin</methodname> method of the <methodname>UserBusinessActivity</methodname>
   class. A client can terminate a business activity by calling the <methodname>close</methodname> method, and cancel it
   by calling the <methodname>cancel</methodname> method.
      </para>
      <para>
   If any of the Web Services invoked by the client register for the
   <systemitem>BusinessActivityWithCoordinatorCompletion</systemitem> protocol, the client can call the
   <methodname>completed</methodname> method before calling the <methodname>close</methodname> method, to notify the
   services that it has finished making service invocations in the current activity.
      </para>
      <para>
   More complex business activity management, such as suspension and resumption of business activities, is supported by
   the <classname>BusinessActivityManagerFactory</classname> and <classname>BusinessActivityManager</classname> classes.
      </para>
      <para>
   Full details of the WS-AT APIs are provided in <xref linkend="sec-xts-api" />.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Client-Side Handler Configuration</title>

      <para>
   XTS does not require the client application to use a specific API to perform invocations on transactional Web
   Services. The client is free to use any appropriate API to send SOAP messages to the server and receive SOAP
   responses.  The only requirements imposed on the client are:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
     <para>
       It must forward details of the current transaction to the server when invoking a web service.
     </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
     <para>
       It must process any responses from the server in the context of the correct transaction.
     </para>
   </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
   In order to achieve this, the client must insert details of the current XTS context into the headers of outgoing SOAP
   messages, and extract the context details from the headers of incoming messages and associate the context with the
   current thread. To simplify this process, the XTS module includes handlers which can perform this task
   automatically. These handlers are designed to work with JAX-WS clients.
      </para>
      
      <note>
   <para>
     If you choose to use a different SOAP client/server infrastructure for business service invocations, you must
     provide for header processing. XTS only provides interceptors for or JAX-WS. A JAX-RPC handler is provided only for
     the 1.0 implementation.
   </para>
      </note>
      <!--
      <section> <title>JAX-RPC Client Context Handlers</title> <para> To register the JAX-RPC client-side context
      handler used by the client applications, a handler chain must be included in the definition of the
      <varname>service-ref</varname> in the client's <filename>web.xml</filename> deployment descriptor.  Please refer
      to the example application located in <filename>ddrpc/jboss/client-web-app.xml</filename> for an example of such a
      handler.  </para> <para> You need to instantiate the
      <classname>com.arjuna.mw.wst11.client.JaxRPCHeaderContextProcessor</classname> class when registering a JAX-RPC
      client context handler.  </para> <note> <para> A JAX-RPC client handler is not provided for the 1.1
      implementation.  </para> </note> </section>
      -->
      <section>
   <title>JAX-WS Client Context Handlers</title>
   <para>
     In order to register the JAX-WS client-side context handler, the client application uses the APIs provided by the
     <classname>javax.xml.ws.BindingProvider</classname> and <classname>javax.xml.ws.Binding</classname> classes, to
     install a handler chain on the service proxy which is used to invoke the remote endpoint. Refer to the example
     application client implementation located in the
     <filename>src/com/jboss/jbosstm/xts/demo/BasicClient.java</filename> file for an example.
   </para>
   <para>
     You can also specify the handlers by using a configuration file deployed with the application. The file is
     identified by attaching a <systemitem>javax.jws.HandlerChain</systemitem> annotation to the interface class, which
     declares the JAX-WS client API. This interface is normally generated from the web service WSDL port definition.
   </para>
   <para>
     You need to instantiate the <classname>com.arjuna.mw.wst11.client.JaxWSHeaderContextProcessor</classname> class
     when registering a JAX-WS client context handler.
   </para>
   <!--
   <note> <para> The class used in the 1.1 implementation is
   <classname>com.arjuna.mw.wst11.client.JaxWSHeaderContextProcessor</classname>.  </para> </note>
   -->
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Creating Transactional Web Services</title>

    <para>
      The two parts to implementing a Web service using XTS are the transaction management and the business logic.
    </para>
    <para>
      The bulk of the transaction management aspects are organized in a clear and easy-to-implement model by means of
      the XTS’s <firstterm>Participant API</firstterm>, provides a structured model for negotiation between the web
      service and the transaction coordinator. It allows the web service to manage its own local transactional data, in
      accordance with the needs of the business logic, while ensuring that its activities are in step with those of the
      client and other services involved in the transaction. Internally, this API uses SOAP to invokes operations on the
      various WS-C, WS-AT and WS-BA services, to drive the transaction to completion.
    </para>
    
    <section>
      <title>Participants</title>
      <para>
   A <firstterm>participant</firstterm> is a software entity which is driven by the transaction manager on behalf of a
   Web service. When a web service wants to participate in a particular transaction, it must enroll a participant to act
   as a proxy for the service in subsequent negotiations with the coordinator. The participant implements an API
   appropriate to the type of transaction it is enrolled in, and the participant model selected when it is enrolled. For
   example, a Durable2PC participant, as part of a WS-Atomic Transaction, implements the Durable2PCParticipant
   interface.  The use of participants allows the transactional control management aspects of the Web service to be
   factored into the participant implementation, while staying separate from the the rest of the Web service's business
   logic and private transactional data management.
      </para>
      <para>
   The creation of participants is not trivial, since they ultimately reflect the state of a Web service’s back-end
   processing facilities, an aspect normally associated with an enterprise’s own IT infrastructure. Implementations must
   use one of the following interfaces, depending upon the protocol it will participate within:
   <interfacename>com.arjuna.wst11.Durable2PCParticipant</interfacename>,
   <interfacename>com.arjuna.wst11.Volatile2PCParticipant</interfacename>,
   <interfacename>com.arjuna.wst11.BusinessAgreementWithParticipantCompletionParticipant</interfacename>, or
   <interfacename>com.arjuna.wst11.BusinessAgreementWithCoordinatorCompletionParticipant</interfacename>.
      </para>
      <para>
   A full description of XTS’s participant features is provided in <remark>Fix me</remark>.
      </para>
<!--
      <note> <para> The 1.1 XTS implementation expects participants to implement the same APIs as the 1.0
      implementation.  </para> </note>
-->
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Service-Side Handler Configuration</title>
      <para>
   A transactional Web service must ensure that a service invocation is included in the appropriate transaction. This
   usually only affects the operation of the participants and has no impact on the operation of the rest of the Web
   service. XTS simplifies this task and decouples it from the business logic, in much the same way as for transactional
   clients<remark>Add an xref</remark>. XTS provides a handler which detects and extracts the context details from the
   headers in incoming SOAP headers, and associates the web service thread with the transaction. The handler clears this
   association when dispatching SOAP responses, and writes the context into the outgoing message headers. This is shown
   in <xref linkend="fig-context-handlers-registered-with-soap-server" />.
      </para>
      <para>
   The service side handlers for JAX-WS come in two different versions. The normal handler resumes any transaction
   identified by an incoming context when the service is invoked, and suspends this transaction when the service call
   completes. The alternative handler is used to interpose a local coordinator. The first time an incoming parent
   context is seen, the local coordinator service creates a subordinate transaction, which is resumed before the web
   service is called. The handler ensures that this subordinate transaction is resumed each time the service is invoked
   with the same parent context. When the subordinate transaction completes, the association between the parent
   transaction and its subordinate is cleared.
      </para>
      <note>
   <para>
     The subordinate service side handler is only able to interpose a subordinate coordinator for an Atomic Transaction.
   </para>
      </note>
      <note>
   <para>
     JAX-RPC is provided for the 1.0 implementation only.
   </para>
      </note>
      <!--
      <section>
   <title>JAX-RPC Service Context Handlers</title>

   <para> In order to register the JAX-RPC server-side context handler with the deployed Web Services, you must include
   a handler chain in the Web Services deployment descriptor.  Please refer to the example application located in the
   <filename>ddrpc/jboss/webservices.xml</filename> deployment descriptor for an example.  </para> <para> When
   registering a normal JAX-RPC service context handler, you must instantiate the
   <classname>com.arjuna.mw.wst11.service.JaxRPCHeaderContextProcessor</classname> class. If you need coordinator
   interposition, you need to employ the
   <classname>com.arjuna.mw.wst11.service.JaxRPCSubordinateHeaderContextProcessor</classname> instead.  </para> <note>
   <para> A JAX-RPC client handler is not provided for the 1.1 implementation.  </para> </note> </section>
      -->
      <section>
   <title>JAX-WS Service Context Handlers</title>
   <para>
     To register the JAX-WS server-side context handler with the deployed Web Services, you must install a handler chain
     on the Server Endpoint Implementation class. The endpoint implementation class annotation, which is the one
     annotated with a <systemitem>javax.jws.WebService</systemitem>, must be supplemented with a
     <systemitem>javax.jws.HandlerChain</systemitem> annotation which identifies a handler configuration file deployed
     with the application. Please refer to the example application configuration file located at
     <filename>dd/jboss/context-handlers.xml</filename> and the endpoint implementation classes located in
     <filename>src/com/jboss/jbosstm/xts/demo/services</filename> for an example.
   </para>
   <para>
     When registering a normal JAX-WS service context handler, you must instantiate the
     <classname>com.arjuna.mw.wst11.service.JaxWSHeaderContextProcessor</classname> class. If you need coordinator
     interposition, employ the <classname>com.arjuna.mw.wst11.service.JaxWSSubordinateHeaderContextProcessor</classname>
     instead.
   </para>
   <!--
       <note> <para> The classes used in the 1.1 implementation are
       <classname>com.arjuna.mw.wst11.service.JaxWSHeaderContextProcessor</classname> and
       <classname>com.arjuna.mw.wst11.service.JaxWSSubordinateHeaderContextProcessor</classname>.  </para> </note>
   -->
   <figure id="fig-context-handlers-registered-with-soap-server">
     <title>Context Handlers Registered with the SOAP Server</title>
     <mediaobject>
       <imageobject>
         <imagedata fileref="images/fig-context-handlers-registered-with-soap-server.png" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
       <textobject>
         <para></para>
       </textobject>
     </mediaobject>
   </figure>

      </section>
    </section>

<!--
    <section> <title>Implementing the Web Service Business Logic</title> <para> Details about the context management
    that the context processor performs are normally unimportant to the Web service application logic as well as work
    performed by other protocol-specific context handlers. However, back-end systems used by the Web service application
    logic, such as databases, need to track the front-end transaction context, in order to map any operations invoked
    within its scope onto a back-end transaction context.  </para> <para> The back-end typically wraps a database driver
    in a decorator pattern which extends the interface of the original driver to hook into the service-side API, so that
    it can access the transaction context details. The general architecture for this pattern is shown in <xref
    linkend="fig-back-end-pattern" />.  </para> <figure id="fig-back-end-pattern"> <title>General Pattern for Back-End
    Integration, from the Service Side</title> <mediaobject> <imageobject> <imagedata
    fileref="images/fig-back-end-pattern.png" format="PNG"/> </imageobject> </mediaobject> </figure> <para> The missing
    element in <xref linkend="fig-back-end-pattern" /> is the <systemitem>commit</systemitem> protocol which allows
    back-end work to be made durable or roll back at the end of a transaction. This is covered in the <remark>Add an
    xref</remark> participant chapter, which explores the participant/back-end relation.  </para> </section>
-->
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Summary</title>

    <para>
      This chapter gives a high-level overview of each of the major software pieces used by the Web Services
      transactions component of JBoss Transaction Service. The Web Services transaction manager provided by JBoss
      Transaction Service is the hub of the architecture and is the only piece of software that user-level software does
      not bind to directly. XTS provides header-processing infrastructure for use with Web Services transactions
      contexts for both client applications and Web Services. XTS provides a simple interface for developing transaction
      participants, along with the necessary document-handling code.
    </para>
    <para>
      This chapter is only an overview, and does not address the more difficult and subtle aspects of programming Web
      Services. For fuller explanations of the components, please continue reading.
    </para>
  </section>
</chapter>

