<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "../project_documentation.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<section id="_container_integration">
    <title>Container Integration</title>
    <para>
        The RESTAT protocol described here is implemented as a JAX-RS service, deploys as a Servlet 3.0
        application and depends on the Narayana TM as the back-end transaction engine. JAX-RS is the Java language
        support for building REST based applications - it is both an annotation-based API for defining resources and
        a run-time for mapping HTTP requests to Java methods. Thus any container supporting these two requirements
        (servlet 3.0 and the Narayana TM) can be used.
    </para>
    <section id="_deploying_as_a_wildfly_subsystem">
        <title>Deploying as a Wildfly Subsystem</title>
        <para>
            The RESTAT coordinator is integrated with the 8.0.0.Alpha3 and subsequent releases of the Wildfly
            application server (
            <ulink url="http://www.wildfly.org/download/">http://www.wildfly.org/download/</ulink>
            ) as a subsystem (called RTS) so you do not have to explicitly deploy it. You do, however, need to start
            the application server using an optional server configuration:
        </para>
        <screen> change directory to where the application server is installed
            Linux: ./bin/standalone.sh --server-config=../../docs/examples/configs/standalone-rts.xml
            Windows: bin\standalone.bat --server-config=..\..\docs\examples\configs\standalone-rts.xml
        </screen>
        <para>
            For this mode of deployment the
            <systemitem>transaction-manager</systemitem>
            URI is
            <ulink url="http://&lt;host&gt;:&lt;port&gt;/rest-at-coordinator/tx/transaction-manager">http://&lt;host&gt;:&lt;port&gt;/rest-at-coordinator/tx/transaction-manager</ulink>
        </para>
    </section>
    <section id="_deploying_into_a_servlet_container">
        <title>Deploying into a Servlet Container</title>
        <para>
            For other versions of the application server you will need to deploy the coordinator as a war
            archive using the standard war deployment mechanism appropriate to your particular container. The
            archive is contained in the bin folder of the narayana download (restat-web.war). If you are building
            from source the archive is located in rts/at/webservice/target/restat-web-&lt;version&gt;.war.</para>
        <para>
            For this mode of deployment the
            <systemitem>transaction-manager</systemitem>
            URI is
            <ulink url="http://&lt;host&gt;:&lt;port&gt;/rest-tx/tx/transaction-manager">http://&lt;host&gt;:&lt;port&gt;/rest-tx/tx/transaction-manager</ulink>
        </para>
    </section>
</section>
