<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "Transaction_Bridging_Guide.ent">
]>
<appendix>
  <title>Design Notes</title>
  <section>
    <title>General Points</title>
    <para>This section records key design points relating to the bridge implementation. The target
      audience for this section is software engineers maintaining or extending the transaction
      bridge implementation. It is unlikely to contain material useful to users, except in so far as
      they wish to contribute to the project. An in-depth knowledge of JBossTS internals may be
      required to make sense of some parts of this appendix.</para>
    <para>The txbridge is written as far as possible as a user application layered on top of the JTA
      and XTS implementations. It accesses these underlying components through standard or supported
      APIs as far as possible. For example, XAResource is favored over AbstractRecord, the JCA
      standard XATerminator is used for driving subordinates and so on. This facilitates modularity
      and portability.</para>
    <para>It follows that functionality required by the bridge should first be evaluated for
      inclusion in one of the underlying modules, as experience has shown it is often also useful
      for other user applications. For example, improvements to allows subordinate termination code
      portability between JTA and JTS, and support for subordinate crash recovery have benefited
      from this approach. The txbridge remains a thin layer on top of this functionality, containing
      only purpose specific code.</para>
    <para>The 'loops and diamonds' problem boils down to providing deterministic, bi-directional 1:1
      mapping between an Xid (which is fixed length) and a WS-AT context (which is unbounded length
      in the spec, although bounded for instances created by the XTS). Consistent hashing techniques
      get you so far with independent operation, but the only 100% solution is to have a shared
      service on the network providing the mapping lookup. Naturally this then becomes a single
      point of failure as well as a scalability issue. For some scenarios it may be possible to use
      interceptors to propagate the Xid on the web services call as extra data, instead of trying to
      reproduce the mapping at the other end. Unfortunately XA does not provide for this kind of
      extensibility, although CORBA does, leading to the possibility of solving the issue without a
      centralized approach in mixed JTS+WS-AT environments.</para>
    <para>Requiring a tx context on all calls is a bit limiting, but JBossWS native lacks a
      WS-Policy implementation. Things may change with the move to CXF. This is really a wider issue
      with XTS, not just the bridge.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Crash Recovery Considerations</title>
    <para>As usual with transactions, it's the crash recovery that provides for the most complexity.
      Recovery for the inbound and outbound sides is handled independently. Because of event
      ordering between recovery modules (JTA, XTS), it requires two complete cycles to resolve some
      of these crash recovery situations.</para>
    <section>
      <title>Inbound Crash Recovery</title>
      <para>An inbound transaction involves at least
        four log writes. Top down (i.e. in reverse order
        of log creation) these are: The WS-AT coordinator
        log
        (assumed here to be XTS, but may be 3rd
        party), the XTS Participant log in the receiving server, the
        JCA Subordinate transaction log
        and at least one XA Resource Manager log (which are 3rd party e.g.
        Oracle). 
      </para>
      <para>There is no separate log created by the txbridge. The XTS Participant log inlines the
        Serializable
        BridgeDurableParticipant via its writeObject method. Recorded state includes its
        identity (the Xid) and
        the identity of the separately logged JTA subordinate tx (a Uid).
      </para>
      <para>XTS is responsible for
        the top level coordinator log. JBossTS is responsible for the JTA
        subordinate tx log and 3rd party
        RMs
        are each responsible for their own.</para>
      <para>The following situations may exist at recovery time,
        according to the point in time at
        which the crash occurred:</para>
      <para>RM log only: In this case, the
        InboundBridgeRecoveryManager's XAResourceOrphanFilter
        implementation will be invoked via JBossTS XARecoveryModule,
        will recognize the orphaned Xids
        by their formatId (which they inherit from the JCA subordinate,
        which
        the txbridge previously
        created with a specially constructed inflowed Xid) and will vote to have
        the
        XARecoveryModule
        roll them back as no corresponding JCA subordinate log exists, so presumed abort applies.
      </para>
      <para>RM log and JTA subordinate tx log: The InboundBridgeRecoverytManager's scan of indoubt
        subordinate JTA transactions identifies the JTA subordinate as being orphaned and rolls it
        back, which
        in turn causes the rollback of the RM's XAResource.</para>
      <para>RM log, JTA subordinate log and XTS
        Participant log: XTS is responsible for detecting
        that the Participant is orphaned (by re-sending Prepared
        to the Coordinator and receiving
        'unknown tx' back) and initiating rollback under the
        presumed abort
        convention.</para>
      <para>WS-AT coordinator log and all downstream logs: The coordinator re-sends Commit
        to the
        Participant and the transaction completes.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Outbound Crash Recovery</title>
      <para>An outbound transaction involves log writes for the JTA parent transaction and the XTS
        BridgeWrapper coordinator. There is not a separate log created by the txbridge. The JTA tx
        log inlines the Serializable BridgeXAResource via its writeObject method. Recorded state
        includes the JTA tx id and bridgeWrapper id String. In addition a Web Service participating
        in the subordinate transaction will create a log. Assuming it's XTS, the participant side
        log will inline any Serializable Durable2PCParticipant, effectively forming the RM log.
      </para>
      <para>The following situations may exist at recovery time, according to the point in time at
        which the crash occurred:</para>
      <para>RM log (i.e. XTS Participant log, inlining Serializable Durable2PCParticipant) only: XTS
        is responsible for detecting that the Participant is orphaned (its direct parent, the
        subordinate coordinator, is missing) and rolling it back. The bridge recovery code is not
        involved – XTS recovery deserializes and drives any app DurableParticipants directly.</para>
      <para>RM log and XTS subordinate log: The DurableParticipant(s) (i.e. client side) and XTS
        subordinate coordinator / BridgeWrapper (i.e. server side) and reinstantiated by XTS. The
        BridgeWrapper, being subordinate to a missing parent, must be identified and explicitly
        rolledback by the bridge recovery code. The bridge recovery manager is itself a
        RecoveryModule, thus invoked periodically to perform this task. It identified its own
        BridgeWrapper instance from amongst all those awaiting recovery by means of an id prefix
        specific to the txbridge code. See JBTM-725 for further details.</para>
      <para>RM log, XTS subordinate log and JTA parent log (with inlined BridgeXAResource): Top down
        recovery by the JTA recovery module drives tx to completion, taking the normal JTA
        parent->BridgeXAResource->XTS subordinate->DurableParticipant path. Note that if the bridge
        is the only XAResource in the parent, the JTA must have 1PC commit optimization disabled or
        it won't write a log for recovery.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Test framework</title>
    <para>The test suite for the txbridge is split along two axis. Firstly, the inbound and outbound
      sides of the bridge have their own test suites in a parallel code package hierarchy. These are
      largely mirrors, containing tests which have matching intent but different implementation
      details. Secondly, the tests are split between those for normal execution and those for crash
      recovery.</para>
    <para>The tests use a framework consisting of a basic servlet acting as client (the code
      pre-dates the availability of XTS lightweight client), a basic web service as server and a set
      of utility classes implementing the appropriate interfaces
      (Participant/Synchronization/XAResource). These classes contain the bare minimum of test
      logic. In order to make the tests as easy to understand and modify as possible, an attempt is
      made to capture the entirety of the test logic within the junit test function instead of
      splitting it over the framework classes. To facilitate this, extensive use is made of byteman
      and its associated dtest library, which provides basic distributed mock-like execution tracing
      and configuration. You probably need to take a detour and read the dtest docs before
      proceeding further.</para>
    <para>The basic tests all follow the same pattern: make a call through the bridge, following
      different logic paths in each test, and verify that the test resources see the expected method
      calls. For example, in a test that runs a transaction successfully, expect to see commit
      called on enlisted resources and rollback not called. For a test that configures the prepare
      to fail, expect to see rollback called and commit not called. The tests verify behavior in the
      presence of 'expected' errors e.g. prepare failures, but generally don't cover unexpected
      failures e.g. exceptions thrown from commit.</para>
    <para>Test normal execution targets in the tests/build.xml assume the server is started manually
      with byteman installed and has XTS, txbridge and the test artifacts deployed. Note that it
      also contains targets that may be called to achieve the last of these steps.</para>
    <para>The crash rec tests start (and subsequently restart) the server automatically, but assume
      the that XTS, txbridge and the test artifacts are deployed. To manage the server they need to
      be provided with JBOSS_HOME and JAVA_HOME values in the build.xml.</para>
  </section>
</appendix>
