<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "Transaction_Bridging_Guide.ent">
]>
<chapter>
  <title>Using the Transaction Bridge</title>
  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>This section describes how to use the transaction bridge in your applications. It is
      recommended you first read the preceding chapters for a theoretical background in the way the
      bridge functions.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Deployment</title>
    <para>
      The txbridge.jar file should be placed in JBossAS server/lt;config&gt;/deploy directory.
      The server must also be running JBossTS JTA (the default transaction manager) or JTS, and also
      JBossTS XTS. The versions of all these components must be consistent.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Inbound Bridging</title>
    <para>To use the inbound bridge, register the JAX-WS handler into the handler chain of any Web
      Service as follows:</para>
    <example>
      <title>
        Registering the
        <literal>handler</literal>
        for Inbound Bridging
      </title>
      <programlisting role="XML" language="XML"><xi:include href="extras/inboundbridging.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" parse="text" /></programlisting>
    </example>
    <para>The web service may then operate as though running in the scope of a JTA transaction, as
      indeed it is. For example, it can call (or indeed simply be) an EJB3 business logic method
      annotated with @TansactionAttribute(TransactionAttributeType.MANDATORY).</para>
    <para>Note that the handlers expect a WS-AT transaction context to be present on all inbound
      invocations. If you wish deploy your service in such a way as to make transactional invocation
      optional, you must expose it though two different endpoints, one transactional and one not,
      with the handlers registered only on the former. This limitation may be addressed in future
      versions.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Outbound Bridging</title>
    <para>To use the outbound bridge, register the JAX-WS handler into the handler chain of any Web
      Service client application as follows:</para>
    <example>
      <title>
        Registering the
        <literal>handler</literal>
        for Outbound Bridging
      </title>
      <programlisting role="XML" language="XML"><xi:include href="extras/outboundbridging.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" parse="text" /></programlisting>
    </example>
    <para>The web service client may then make calls to web service implementations that expect to
      be invoked in the scope of a WS-AT transaction.</para>
    <para>Note that the handlers expect a JTA transaction context to be present on the client thread
      used to make the outbound web service invocation. If the context is not always present,
      different stubs must be used for the transactional and non-transactional cases and the handler
      chain registered only on the former. This limitation may be addressed in future versions.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Demonstration Application</title>
    <para>A simple demonstration application is available to show usage of the bridge. It is modeled
      to some extent on the XTS 'Night Out' demonstrator application, with which readers are assumed
      to be familiar.</para>
    <para>Since transactions mostly run without visible effect, the demo is useful mainly as an
      example of how to utilize the bridge. The bridge implementation does however contain trace
      level
      logging for most functions. Used in conjunction with verbose logging from XTS, the
      transaction
      manager, the Web Service stack and the EJB container, this can be used to gain a
      detailed
      understanding of the flow of events in the system. Alternatively, stepping though the
      demo using
      a source debugger can be instructive.</para>
    <para>
      To deploy and run the demo application, edit demo/build.xml to ensure the jbossas.home and
      jbossas.server properties are set correctly, then execute 'ant dist' to build the application
      artifacts. Start the application server, then deploy the service side of the demo using 'ant
      deploy-service' Once it has deployed, the client app can be similarly installed using 'ant
      deploy-client'. Depending on your server configuration, the client will then be accessible
      from
      e.g.
      <ulink url="http://localhost:8080/txbridge-demo-client/">http://localhost:8080/txbridge-demo-client/</ulink>
    </para>
    <section>
      <title>Inbound Bridge</title>
      <para>The demonstrator exposes a EJB3 SLSB as a transactional web service ('Bistro') via the
        inbound bridge. Note that the code implementing this service is standard EJB with JSR-181
        annotations and has no compile time dependency on XTS or the txbridge. The only point of
        linkage is the usage of the @HandlerChain(file = "jaxws-handlers-server.xml") annotation to
        reference a xml file containing the XTS and txbridge handlers, as detailed above. Other than
        this the service side of the application uses only standard JavaEE elements and has no
        direct knowledge of WS-AT transactions.</para>
      <para>A client starts a WS-AT transaction and makes an invocation on the web service. The
        client does not use JTA (XA) transactions. It uses @HandlerChain(file =
        "jaxws-handlers-client.xml") to register the XTS header context processor, but is otherwise
        similar to the XTS demo client.</para>
      <para>
        In this demo, the inbound bridge converts the WS-AT context to a JTA one and invokes the
        EJB
        in that scope. By default the EJB is backed by the hsqldb embedded in JBossAS, for ease
        of
        deployment. This database does not support XA, so the resource registered for it uses
        LRCO.
        However, this point is not significant to the demo. Curious uses can readily use a true
        XA
        database by deploying it into JBossAS via the usual &lt;xa-datasource&gt; in a -ds.xml
        file, then alter the demo's dd/persistence.xml to reference it.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Outbound Bridge</title>
      <para>The demonstrator client application can also be used to invoke the XTS Night Out demo
        Restaurant Service via the outbound bridge. Deploy the XTS demo application services, then
        select the 'JTA' transaction type in the client. In this scenario the client uses a JTA
        transaction only, whilst the service understands WS-AT type transactions only. Note that the
        client has its own copy of the service API, annotated with @HandlerChain(file =
        "jaxws-handlers-client.xml"), which is the only point of linkage with the transaction
        bridge. Once again neither the client nor server have any compile time dependency on the
        bridge.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Loops and Diamonds</title>
    <para>In distributed environments that utilize transaction bridging, it is possible to construct
      arrangements of servers such that a transaction context passes though more than one
      interposition. These can give rise to some undesirable issues, including locking and
      performance problems.</para>
    <para>A simple case would be a loop in which a JTA transaction context is bridged outbound to a
      WS-AT context, passed though one or more remote servers and inflowed back to the original
      server through an inbound bridge. This may result in a new subordinate JTA context, rather
      than reuse of the existing parent context in the original server.</para>
    <para>This situation has two main observable effects. Firstly, the parent JTA transaction and
      indirectly subordinate JTA transaction are considered distinct and XAResources may not be
      shared between them. In most cases this will cause isolation between the transactions, such
      that they do not share locks or see eachother's changes. This may cause deadlocks in the
      application. Secondly, performance will be poor relative to reuse of the original context,
      particularly if the interposition chain becomes long.</para>
    <para>A similar problem exists where a transaction context is propagated from a single source to
      a single destination server via two or more separate routes, the abstract paths forming a
      diamond shape. In such case the intermediate nodes operate independently and will bridge the
      original context to two separate interposed contexts. To the destination server these will
      appear unrelated, rather than as representations of the same transaction. Thus instead of
      recombining into a single shared transaction context at the destination, they will behave as
      different transactions, giving rise once again to potential deadlock and performance issues.
    </para>
    <para>These problems may be partially addressed by having a shared context mapping service
      available on the network, which each bridge consults when working with a previously unseen
      transaction context for the first time. Using such a mechanism, bridge instances may identify
      transactions for which an established mapping already exists and reuse that relationship
      rather than creating a new one.</para>
    <para>This shared service model does however cause some issues of its own with regard to
      performance and availability. It is not currently implemented. Therefore, users are urged to
      be cautious when constructing distributed applications. Whilst location abstraction is
      sometimes desirable, is is important to maintain a clear understanding of the deployment
      relationships between transactional components in the system.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Distributed JTA and the JTS</title>
    <para>The JavaEE transaction engine in JBossTS comes in two varieties. These are the local only
      JTA, which does not support propagation of transaction context or transaction control calls
      between JVMs and the JTAX, which provides the JTA API implemented by a JTS engine that does
      support distributed usage.</para>
    <para>JBossAS uses the local JTA implementation by default, but can be reconfigured to use the
      JTS via the JTA API, such that it supports distributed transactions without requiring any
      changes to business applications.</para>
    <para>In environments requiring transaction propagation of JTA transactions, it is feasible to
      use either the JTS or an outbound and inbound bridge pair to achieve this. In the former case
      the transport is RMI/IIOP for the transaction control and RMI/IIOP or JRMP for the
      transactional business logic calls. In the latter case the transport is Web Services for both
      transaction control and business logic.</para>
    <para>From a transaction management perspective the JTS solution is preferred, due to simplicity
      (no protocol mapping is needed), maturity (JBossTS JTS was the world's first JTS
      implementation and has been extensively used and tested in production environments) and
      performance (binary vs. xml).</para>
    <para>It is possible to use transactions that propagate context on some calls via JTS and on
      others via Web Services, such as a client invoking both EJBs via RMI/IIOP and Web services
      with WS-AT context. In such cases it's possible for a transaction to have multiple
      representations that the infrastructure cannot determine are related, even if they actually
      represent different contexts in the same interposition hierarchy. Care must therefore be taken
      to avoid the problems described previously in 'Loops and Diamonds'.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Logging</title>
    <para>The transaction bridge uses the jboss-logging system. When running inside JBossAS 6,
      logging is configured via the server's deploy/jboss-logging.xml file. To enable full logging
      for the transaction bridge, which may be useful for debug purposes, the following should be
      used:</para>
    <example>
      <title>Configuring Transaction Bridge Logging</title>
      <programlisting role="XML" language="XML"><xi:include href="extras/txbridgelogging.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" parse="text" /></programlisting>
    </example>
    <para>Note that the transaction bridge is a thin layer on top of the XTS and JTA/JTS components
      of
      JBossTS, and that it also interacts with other parts of the application server. To gain a
      comprehensive understanding of the system's operation, it may be necessary to enable verbose
      logging for some of these other components also. The JBossTS logging system is discussed in
      detail in the accompanying documentation set, but for ease of reference the following may be
      used to enable verbose logging:</para>
    <example>
      <title>Configuring verbose logging</title>
      <programlisting role="XML" language="XML"><xi:include href="extras/verboselogging.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" parse="text" /></programlisting>
    </example>
    <para>Note also that deployment ordering issues can result in JBossTS components, including the
      transaction bridge, becoming active before the logging system is fully configured. In such
      cases a default logging level may apply during startup, resulting in some more detailed debug
      messages being missed.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
