<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "ArjunaTA_Development_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter>
  <title>Examples</title>
  
  <section>
    <title>JDBC example</title>

    <example>
      <title>JDBC example</title>
      <para>
        This simplified example assumes that you are using the transactional JDBC driver provided with JBossTS. For
        details about how to configure and use this driver see the previous Chapter.<!-- Link? -->
      </para>
      <programlisting language="Java" role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/jdbc_example.java" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" parse="text" /></programlisting>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Failure recovery example with BasicXARecovery</title>
    <para>
      This class implements the <interfacename>XAResourceRecovery</interfacename> interface for XAResources. The parameter supplied in <varname>setParameters</varname>
      can contain arbitrary information necessary to initialize the class once created. In this example, it contains the
      name of the property file in which the database connection information is specified, as well as the number of
      connections that this file contains information on. Each item is separated by a semicolon.
    </para>
    <para>
      This is only a small example of the sorts of things an XAResourceRecovery implementer could do. This implementation
      uses a property file that is assumed to contain sufficient information to recreate connections used during the
      normal run of an application so that recovery can be performed on them. Typically, user-names and passwords should
      never be presented in raw text on a production system.
    </para>
    <example>
      <title>Database parameter format for the properties file</title>
      <screen>
 DB_x_DatabaseURL=
 DB_x_DatabaseUser=
 DB_x_DatabasePassword=
 DB_x_DatabaseDynamicClass=
      </screen>
      <para>
        <replaceable>x</replaceable> is the number of the connection information.
      </para>
    </example>
    <para>
      Some error-handling code is missing from this example, to make it more readable.
    </para>
    <example>
      <title>Failure recovery example with BasicXARecovery</title>
      <programlisting language="Java" role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/failure_recovery_example.java" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" parse="text" /></programlisting>
      <para>
        You can use the class <classname>com.arjuna.ats.internal.jdbc.recovery.JDBC2RecoveryConnection</classname> to
        create a new connection to the database using the same parameters used to create the initial connection.
      </para>
    </example>
  </section>
</chapter>

