<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "ArjunaTA_Development_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter>
  <title>Using JBossJTA in application servers</title>
  <para>
    JBoss Application Server is discussed here. Refer to the documentation for your application server for differences.
  </para>
  <section>
    <title>Configuration</title>
    <para>
      When JBossJTA runs embedded in JBossAS, the transaction system is configured primarily through the
      <filename>transaction-jboss-beans.xml</filename> deployment descriptor, which overrides properties read from the
      default properties file embedded in the .<filename>jar</filename> file.
    </para>
    <table>
      <title>Common configuration attributes</title>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>CoordinatorEnvironmentBean.defaultTimeout</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>
                The default transaction timeout to be used for new transactions.  Specified as an integer in seconds.
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>CoordinatorEnvironmentBean.enableStatistics</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>
                This determines whether or not the transaction service should gather statistical information.  This
                information can then be viewed using the TransactionStatistics MBean.  Specified as a Boolean. The
                default is to not gather this information.
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <para>
      See the <filename>transaction-jboss-beans.xml</filename> file and the JBoss Application Server administration and
      configuration guide for further information.
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Logging</title>
    <para>
      To make JBossTS logging semantically consistent with JBossAS, the
      <interfacename>TransactionManagerService</interfacename> modifies the level of some log messages, by overriding
      the value of the <varname>LoggingEnvironmentBean.loggingFactory</varname> property in the
      <filename>jbossts-properties.xml</filename> file. Therefore, the value of this property has no effect on the
      logging behavior when running embedded in JBossAS. By forcing use of the <systemitem>log4j_releveler</systemitem>
      logger, the <interfacename>TransactionManagerService</interfacename> changes the level of all
      <literal>INFO</literal> level messages in the transaction code to <literal>DEBUG</literal>.  Therefore, these
      messages do not appear in log files if the filter level is <literal>INFO</literal>. All other log messages behave
      as normal.
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>The services</title>
    <para>
      The <interfacename>TransactionManager</interfacename> bean provides transaction management services to other
      components in JBossAS. There are two different version of this bean and they requires different configuation. Take
      care to select the <filename>transaction-jboss-beans.xml</filename> suitable for your needs (local JTA or JTS).
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Ensuring transactional context is propatated to the server</title>
    <para>
      You can coordinate transactions from a coordinator which is not located within the JBoss server
      , such as when using transactions created by an external OTS server.  To ensure the transaction context is propagated via
      JRMP invocations to the server, the transaction propagation context factory needs to be explicitly set for the
      JRMP invoker proxy.  This is done as follows:
    </para>
    <programlisting language="Java" role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/jrmp_invoker_proxy.java" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" parse="text" /></programlisting>
  </section>


</chapter>

