<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "ArjunaCore_Development_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter>
  <title>Overview</title>
  
  <para>
    This chapter contains a description of the use of the TxCore transaction engine and the <application>Transactional
    Objects for Java (TXOJ)</application> classes and facilities. The classes mentioned in this chapter are the key to
    writing fault-tolerant applications using transactions. Thus, they are described and then applied in the
    construction of a simple application. The classes to be described in this chapter can be found in the
    <package>com.arjuna.ats.txoj</package> and <package>com.arjuna.ats.arjuna</package> packages.
  </para>
  <note>
    <title>Stand-Alone Transaction Manager</title>
    <para>
      Although JBoss Transaction Service can be embedded in various containers, such as JBoss Application Server, it
      remains a stand-alone transaction manager as well. There are no dependencies between the core JBoss Transaction
      Service and any container implementations.
    </para>
  </note>
  
  <section>
    <title>TxCore</title>
    <subtitle>The Transaction Engine</subtitle>
    <para>
      In keeping with the object-oriented view, the mechanisms needed to construct reliable distributed applications are
      presented to programmers in an object-oriented manner. Some mechanisms need to be inherited, for example,
      concurrency control and state management. Other mechanisms, such as object storage and transactions, are
      implemented as TxCore objects that are created and manipulated like any other object.
    </para>
    <note>
      <para>
        When the manual talks about using persistence and concurrency control facilities it assumes that the
        <application>Transactional Objects for Java (TXOJ)</application> classes are being used. If this is not the case
        then the programmer is responsible for all of these issues.
      </para>
    </note>
    <para>
      TxCore exploits object-oriented techniques to present programmers with a toolkit of Java classes from which
      application classes can inherit to obtain desired properties, such as persistence and concurrency control. These
      classes form a hierarchy, part of which is shown in <xref linkend="txcore_class_hierarchy" /> and which will be described later in this document.
    </para>
    <figure id="txcore_class_hierarchy">
      <title>TxCore Class Hierarchy</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/txcore_class_hierarchy.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      Apart from specifying the scopes of transactions, and setting appropriate locks within objects, the application
      programmer does not have any other responsibilities: TxCore and <application>TXOJ</application> guarantee
      that transactional objects will be registered with, and be driven by, the appropriate transactions, and crash
      recovery mechanisms are invoked automatically in the event of failures.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Saving object states</title>
    <para>
      TxCore needs to be able to remember the state of an object for several purposes.
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>recovery</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The state represents some past state of the object.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>persistence</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The state represents the final state of an object at application termination.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>
      Since these requirements have common functionality they are all implemented using the same mechanism: the classes
      <classname>InputObjectState</classname> and <classname>OutputObjectState</classname>. The classes maintain an
      internal array into which instances of the standard types can be contiguously packed or unpacked using appropriate
      <methodname>pack</methodname> or <methodname>unpack</methodname> operations. This buffer is automatically resized
      as required should it have insufficient space. The instances are all stored in the buffer in a standard form
      called <firstterm>network byte order</firstterm>, making them machine independent. Any other
      architecture-independent format, such as XDR or ASN.1, can be implemented simply by replacing the operations with
      ones appropriate to the encoding required.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The object store</title>
    <para>
      Implementations of persistence can be affected by restrictions imposed by the Java SecurityManager. Therefore, the
      object store provided with TxCore is implemented using the techniques of interface and implementation. The current
      distribution includes implementations which write object states to the local file system or database, and remote
      implementations, where the interface uses a client stub (proxy) to remote services.
    </para>
    <para>
      Persistent objects are assigned unique identifiers, which are instances of the <classname>Uid</classname> class,
      when they are created. These identifiers are used to identify them within the object store. States are read using
      the <methodname>read_committed</methodname> operation and written by the <methodname>write_committed</methodname>
      and <methodname>write_uncommitted</methodname> operations.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Recovery and persistence</title>
    <para>
      At the root of the class hierarchy is the class
      <classname>StateManager</classname>. <classname>StateManager</classname> is responsible for object activation and
      deactivation, as well as object recovery. Refer to <xref linkend="StateManager-signature" /> for the simplified
      signature of the class.
    </para>
    <example id="StateManager-signature">
      <title><classname>Statemanager</classname></title>
      <programlisting language="Java" role="JAVA"> <xi:include href="extras/StateManager-signature.java" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" parse="text" /></programlisting>
    </example>
    <para>
      Objects are assumed to be of three possible flavours.
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <title>Three Flavors of Objects</title>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Recoverable</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <classname>StateManager</classname> attempts to generate and maintain appropriate recovery information for
            the object. Such objects have lifetimes that do not exceed the application program that creates them.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Recoverable and Persistent</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The lifetime of the object is assumed to be greater than that of the creating or accessing application, so
            that in addition to maintaining recovery information, <classname>StateManager</classname> attempts to
            automatically load or unload any existing persistent state for the object by calling the
            <methodname>activate</methodname> or <methodname>deactivate</methodname> operation at appropriate times.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Neither Recoverable nor Persistent</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            No recovery information is ever kept, nor is object activation or deactivation ever automatically attempted.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>
      If an object is <phrase>recoverable</phrase> or <phrase>recoverable and persistent</phrase>, then
      <classname>StateManager</classname> invokes the operations <methodname>save_state</methodname> while performing
      <methodname>deactivate</methodname>, and <methodname>restore_state</methodname> while performing
      <methodname>activate</methodname>,) at various points during the execution of the application. These operations
      must be implemented by the programmer since <classname>StateManager</classname> cannot detect user-level state
      changes. <!--(We are examining the automatic generation of default save_state and restore_state operations,
      allowing the programmer to override this when application specific knowledge can be used to improve
      efficiency.)-->This gives the programmer the ability to decide which parts of an object’s state should be made
      persistent. For example, for a spreadsheet it may not be necessary to save all entries if some values can simply
      be recomputed. The <methodname>save_state</methodname> implementation for a class <classname>Example</classname>
      that has integer member variables called A, B and C might be implemented as in <xref linkend="example-save_state"
      />.
    </para>
    <example id="example-save_state">
      <title><methodname>save_state</methodname> Implementation</title>
      <programlisting language="Java" role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/example-save_state.java" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" parse="text" /></programlisting>
    </example>
    <note>
      <para>
        it is necessary for all <methodname>save_state</methodname> and <methodname>restore_state</methodname> methods
        to call <methodname>super.save_state</methodname> and <methodname>super.restore_state</methodname>. This is to
        cater for improvements in the crash recovery mechanisms.
      </para>
    </note>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The life cycle of a Transactional Object for Java</title>
    <para>
      A persistent object not in use is assumed to be held in a passive state, with its state residing in an object
      store and activated on demand. The fundamental life cycle of a persistent object in TXOJ is shown in <xref
      linkend="txoj-lifecycle" />.
    </para>
    <figure id="txoj-lifecycle">
      <title>Lifecycle of a persistent Object in TXOJ</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/txoj-lifecycle.png" format="PNG"/>
        </imageobject>
        <textobject>
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                The object is initially passive, and is stored in the object store as an instance of the class
                <classname>OutputObjectState</classname>.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                When required by an application, the object is automatically activated by reading it from the store
                using a <methodname>read_committed</methodname> operation and is then converted from an
                <classname>InputObjectState</classname> instance into a fully-fledged object by the
                <methodname>restore_state</methodname> operation of the object.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                When the application has finished with the object, it is deactivated by converting it back into an
                <classname>OutputObjectState</classname> instance using the <methodname>save_state</methodname>
                operation, and is then stored back into the object store as a shadow copy using
                <methodname>write_uncommitted</methodname>. This shadow copy can be committed, overwriting the previous
                version, using the <methodname>commit_state</methodname> operation. The existence of shadow copies is
                normally hidden from the programmer by the transaction system. Object deactivation normally only occurs
                when the top-level transaction within which the object was activated commits
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </textobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <note>
      <para>
        During its life time, a persistent object may be made active then passive many times.
      </para>
    </note>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The concurrency controller</title>
    <para>
      The concurrency controller is implemented by the class <classname>LockManager</classname>, which provides sensible
      default behavior while allowing the programmer to override it if deemed necessary by the particular semantics of
      the class being programmed. As with <classname>StateManager</classname> and persistence, concurrency control
      implementations are accessed through interfaces. As well as providing access to remote services, the current
      implementations of concurrency control available to interfaces include:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Local disk/database implementation</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Locks are made persistent by being written to the local file system or database.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>A purely local implementation</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Locks are maintained within the memory of the virtual machine which created them. This implementation has
            better performance than when writing locks to the local disk, but objects cannot be shared between virtual
            machines. Importantly, it is a basic Java object with no requirements which can be affected by the
            SecurityManager.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>
      The primary programmer interface to the concurrency controller is via the <methodname>setlock</methodname>
      operation. By default, the runtime system enforces strict two-phase locking following a multiple reader, single
      writer policy on a per object basis. However, as shown in <xref linkend="txcore_class_hierarchy" />, by inheriting
      from the <classname>Lock</classname> class, you can provide your own lock implementations with different lock
      conflict rules to enable type specific concurrency control.
    </para>
    <para>
      Lock acquisition is, of necessity, under programmer control, since just as <classname>StateManager</classname>
      cannot determine if an operation modifies an object, <classname>LockManager</classname> cannot determine if an
      operation requires a read or write lock. Lock release, however, is under control of the system and requires no
      further intervention by the programmer. This ensures that the two-phase property can be correctly maintained.
    </para>
    <programlisting language="Java" role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/LockManager_class.java" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" parse="text" /></programlisting>
    <para>
      The <classname>LockManager</classname> class is primarily responsible for managing requests to set a lock on an
      object or to release a lock as appropriate. However, since it is derived from <classname>StateManager</classname>,
      it can also control when some of the inherited facilities are invoked. For example,
      <classname>LockManager</classname> assumes that the setting of a write lock implies that the invoking operation
      must be about to modify the object. This may in turn cause recovery information to be saved if the object is
      recoverable. In a similar fashion, successful lock acquisition causes <methodname>activate</methodname> to be
      invoked.
    </para>
    <para>
      <xref linkend="Example_extends_LockManager" /> shows how to try to obtain a write lock on an object.
    </para>
    <example id="Example_extends_LockManager">
      <title><classname>Example</classname> Class</title>
      <programlisting language="Java" role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/Example_extends_LockManager.java" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" parse="text" /></programlisting>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The transactional protocol engine</title>
    <para>
      The transaction protocol engine is represented by the <classname>AtomicAction</classname> class, which uses
      <classname>StateManager</classname> to record sufficient information for crash recovery mechanisms to complete the
      transaction in the event of failures. It has methods for starting and terminating the transaction, and, for those
      situations where programmers need to implement their own resources, methods for registering them with the current
      transaction. Because TxCore supports subtransactions, if a transaction is begun within the scope of an already
      executing transaction it will automatically be nested.
    </para>
    <para>
      You can use TxCore with multi-threaded applications. Each thread within an application can share a transaction or
      execute within its own transaction. Therefore, all TxCore classes are also thread-safe.
    </para>
    <example id="activation_termination_commitment">
      <title>Relationships Between Activation, Termination, and Commitment</title>
      <programlisting language="Java" role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/activation_termination_commitment.java" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" parse="text" /></programlisting>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Creation of bindings to persistent objects</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              This could involve the creation of stub objects and a call to remote objects. Here, we re-bind to an
              existing persistent object identified by <systemitem>Name-A</systemitem>, and a new persistent object. A
              naming system for remote objects maintains the mapping between object names and locations and is described
              in a later chapter.<!--xref-->
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Start of the atomic transaction</term>
          <listitem>
            <para></para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Operation invocations</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              As a part of a given invocation, the object implementation is responsible to ensure that it is locked in
              read or write mode, assuming no lock conflict, and initialized, if necessary, with the latest committed
              state from the object store. The first time a lock is acquired on an object within a transaction the
              object’s state is acquired, if possible, from the object store.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Commit of the top-level action</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              This includes updating of the state of any modified objects in the object store.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Breaking of the  previously created bindings</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The class hierarchy</title>
    <para>
      The principal classes which make up the class hierarchy of TxCore are depicted below.
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><classname>StateManager</classname></para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><classname>LockManager</classname></para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>User-Defined Classes</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><classname>Lock</classname></para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>User-Defined Classes</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><classname>AbstractRecord</classname></para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem><para><classname>RecoveryRecord</classname></para></listitem>
              <listitem><para><classname>LockRecord</classname></para></listitem>
              <listitem><para><classname>RecordList</classname></para></listitem>
              <listitem><para>Other management record types</para></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem><!-- End AbstractRecord -->
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem> <!-- End StateManager -->
      <listitem>
        <para><classname>AtomicAction</classname></para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem><para><classname>TopLevelTransaction</classname></para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem> <!-- End AtomicAction -->
      <listitem>
        <para><classname>Input/OutputObjectBuffer</classname></para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem><para><classname>Input/OutputObjectState</classname></para></listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
      </listitem><!-- End Input/OutputObjectBuffer -->
      <listitem>
        <para><classname>ObjectStore</classname></para>
      </listitem><!-- End ObjectStore -->
    </itemizedlist>

    <!-- Keeping this around in case the other way is hard to read StateManager // Basic naming, persistence and
         recovery control LockManager // Basic two-phase locking concurrency control service User-Defined Classes Lock
         // Standard lock type for multiple readers/single writer User-Defined Lock Classes AbstractRecord // Important
         utility class, similar to Resource RecoveryRecord // handles object recovery LockRecord // handles object
         locking RecordList // Intentions list other management record types AtomicAction // Implements transaction
         control abstraction TopLevelTransaction Input/OutputBuffer // Architecture neutral representation of an
         objects’ state Input/OutputObjectState // Convenient interface to Buffer ObjectStore // Interface to the object
         storage services-->
    <para>
      Programmers of fault-tolerant applications will be primarily concerned with the classes
      <classname>LockManager</classname>, <classname>Lock</classname>, and <classname>AtomicAction</classname>. Other
      classes important to a programmer are <classname>Uid</classname> and <classname>ObjectState</classname>.
    </para>
    <para>
      Most TxCore classes are derived from the base class <classname>StateManager</classname>, which provides primitive
      facilities necessary for managing persistent and recoverable objects. These facilities include support for the
      activation and de-activation of objects, and state-based object recovery.
    </para>
    <para>
      The class <classname>LockManager</classname> uses the facilities of <classname>StateManager</classname> and
      <classname>Lock</classname> to provide the concurrency control required for implementing the serialisability
      property of atomic actions. The concurrency control consists of two-phase locking in the current implementation.
      The implementation of atomic action facilities is supported by <classname>AtomicAction</classname> and
      <classname>TopLevelTransaction</classname>.
    </para>
    <para>
      Consider a simple example. Assume that <classname>Example</classname> is a user-defined persistent class suitably
      derived from the <classname>LockManager</classname>. An application containing an atomic transaction
      <systemitem>Trans</systemitem> accesses an object called <systemitem>O</systemitem> of type <type>Example</type>,
      by invoking the operation <methodname>op1</methodname>, which involves state changes to
      <systemitem>O</systemitem>. The serializability property requires that a write lock must be acquired on
      <systemitem>O</systemitem> before it is modified. Therefore, the body of <methodname>op1</methodname> should
      contain a call to the <methodname>setlock</methodname> operation of the concurrency controller.
    </para>
    <example id="simple_concurrency_control">
      <title>Simple Concurrency Control</title>
      <programlisting language="Java" role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/simple_concurrency_control.java" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" parse="text" /></programlisting>
    </example>
    <procedure>
      <title>Steps followed by the operation <methodname>setlock</methodname></title>
      <para>
        The operation <methodname>setlock</methodname>, provided by the <classname>LockManager</classname> class,
        performs the following functions in <xref linkend="simple_concurrency_control" />.
      </para>
      <step>
        <para>Check write lock compatibility with the currently held locks, and if allowed, continue.</para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Call the StateManager operation <methodname>activate</methodname>.<methodname>activate</methodname> will load,
          if not done already, the latest persistent state of <classname>O</classname> from the object store, then call
          the <classname>StateManager</classname> operation <methodname>modified</methodname>, which has the effect of
          creating an instance of either <classname>RecoveryRecord</classname> or
          <classname>PersistenceRecord</classname> for <classname>O</classname>, depending upon whether
          <classname>O</classname> was persistent or not. The Lock is a WRITE lock so the old state of the object must
          be retained prior to modification. The record is then inserted into the RecordList of Trans.
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Create and insert a <classname>LockRecord</classname> instance in the <classname>RecordList</classname> of
          <systemitem>Trans</systemitem>.
        </para>
      </step>
    </procedure>
    <para>
      Now suppose that action <systemitem>Trans</systemitem> is aborted sometime after the lock has been acquired. Then
      the <methodname>rollback</methodname> operation of <classname>AtomicAction</classname> will process the
      <classname>RecordList</classname> instance associated with <systemitem>Trans</systemitem> by invoking an
      appropriate <methodname>Abort</methodname> operation on the various records. The implementation of this operation
      by the <classname>LockRecord</classname> class will release the WRITE lock while that of
      <classname>RecoveryRecord</classname> or <classname>PersistenceRecord</classname> will restore the prior state of
      <classname>O</classname>.
    </para>
    <para>
      It is important to realise that all of the above work is automatically being performed by TxCore on behalf of the
      application programmer. The programmer need only start the transaction and set an appropriate lock; TxCore and
      <application>TXOJ</application> take care of participant registration, persistence, concurrency control and
      recovery.
    </para>
  </section>
</chapter>

