<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "ArjunaJTS_Installation_And_Administration_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter>
  <title>Preparing Your System</title>
  <procedure>
    <title>Pre-Installation Steps</title>
    <para>
      Before installing the ArjunaJTS software, we recommend the following administrative steps  be taken, assuming a default configuration for ArjunaJTS.
    </para>
    <step>
      <title>Optional but recommended: Create a user and group to run JBossTS.</title>
      <para>
        It is recommended that you create a user and group <literal>arjuna</literal>, using the preferred method for
        your operating system. This user runs the OTS transaction manager, ensuring proper ownership of all the
        transaction logs and the object store, and preventing accidental deletion of these objects by any other users.
      </para>
    </step>
    <step>
      <title>Install the distribution into the required location.</title>
      <para>
   Typically, the distribution is extracted from a <filename>.ZIP</filename> file.
      </para>
    </step>
    <step>
      <title>Specify the Location for the Object Store</title>
      <para>
   ArjunaJTS requires a minimum object store for storing the outcome of transactions in the  event of system crashes. The location of this should be specified in the properties file using the <property>ObjectStoreEnvironmentBean.objectStoreDir</property> key or by using environment
   variable:
      </para>
      <screen><command>java –DObjectStoreEnvironmentBean.objectStoreDir =C:\temp foo.</command></screen>
    </step>
    <step>
      <title>Optional: Specify the sub-directory within the Object Store root.</title>
      <para>
   By default, all object states will be stored within the <filename>defaultStore/</filename> sub-directory of the
   object store root. For instance, if the object store root is
   <filename>/usr/local/Arjuna/TransactionService/ObjectStore</filename>, the subdirectory
   <filename>/usr/local/Arjuna/TransactionService/ObjectStore/defaultStore/</filename> is used.
      </para>
      <para>
   To change this subdirectory, set the <property>ObjectStoreEnvironmentBean.localOSRoot</property> or
   <property>com.arjuna.ats.arjuna.objectstore.localOSRoot</property> property variable accordingly.
      </para>
    </step>
    <step>
      <title>Optional: Change the JTA implementation to use JTS instead of JTA.</title>
      <para>
        If you plan to use the JBossTS transactional JDBC driver, or JTA with the JTS, you must change the JTA
        implementation to use the JTS. You should consult the ArjunaJTS Development Guide or the JTA manuals for
        details.
      </para>
    </step>
  </procedure>
</chapter>
