<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "ArjunaJTS_Development_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter id="chap-ArjunaJTS_Development_Guide-Test_Chapter">
  <title>Constructing an OTS application</title>
  
  <section>
    <title>Important notes for JBossTS</title>
    <section>
      <title>Initialization</title>
      <para>
        JBossTS must be correctly initialized before you create any application object. To guarantee this, use the
        <methodname>initORB</methodname> and <methodname>POA</methodname> methods described in the <citetitle>Orb
        Portability Guide</citetitle>. Consult the <citetitle>Orb Portability Guide</citetitle> if you need direct use
        of the <methodname>ORB_init</methodname> and <methodname>create_POA</methodname> methods provided by the
        underlying ORB.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Implicit context propagation and interposition</title>
      <para>
        If you need implicit context propagation and interposition, initialize JBossTS correctly before you create any
        objects. You can only use implicit context propagation on an ORB which supports filters and interceptors, or the
        <interfacename>CosTSPortability</interfacename> interface. You can set <varname>OTS_CONTEXT_PROP_MODE</varname>
        to <literal>CONTEXT</literal> or <literal>INTERPOSITION</literal>, depending on which functionality you need. If
        you are using the JBossTSA PI, you need to use interposition.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Writing applications using the raw OTS interfaces</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <title>Steps to  participate in an OTS transaction</title>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Create <classname>Resource</classname> and <classname>SubtransactionAwareResource</classname> objects for each
          object which will participate within the transaction or subtransaction. These resources manage the
          persistence, concurrency control, and recovery for the object. The OTS invokes these objects during the
          prepare, commit, or abort phase of the transaction or subtransaction, and the Resources perform the work of
          the application.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Register <classname>Resource</classname> and <classname>SubtransactionAwareResource</classname> objects at the
          correct time within the transaction, and ensure that the object is only registered once within a given
          transaction. As part of registration, a <classname>Resource</classname> receives a reference to a
          <classname>RecoveryCoordinator</classname>. This reference must be made persistent, so that the transaction
          can recover in the event of a failure.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Correctly propagate resources such as locks to parent transactions and
          <classname>SubtransactionAwareResource</classname> objects.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Drive the crash recovery for each resource which was participating within the transaction, in the event of a
          failure.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      The OTS does not provide any <classname>Resource</classname> implementations. You need to provide these
      implementations.  The interfaces defined within the OTS specification are too low-level for most
      situations. JBossTS is designed to make use of raw <firstterm>Common Object Services (COS)</firstterm> interfaces,
      but provides a higher-level API for building transactional applications and framework. This API automates much of
      the work involved with participating in an OTS transaction.
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Transaction context management</title>
    <para>
      If you use implicit transaction propagation, ensure that appropriate objects support the
      <interfacename>TransactionalObject</interfacename> interface. Otherwise, you need to pass the transaction contexts
      as parameters to the relevant operations.
    </para>
    
    <section>
      <title>A transaction originator: indirect and implicit</title>
      <example>
        <title>Indirect and implicit transaction originator</title>
        <programlisting role="JAVA" language="Java"><xi:include href="extras/indirect_and_implicit.java"
        xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" parse="text" /></programlisting>
        <para>
          A transaction originator uses indirect context management and implicit transaction
          propagation. <classname>txn_crt</classname> is a pseudo object supporting the
          <interfacename>Current</interfacename> interface. The client uses the <methodname>begin</methodname> operation
          to start the transaction, which becomes implicitly associated with the originator’s thread of control.
        </para>
        <para>
          The program commits the transaction associated with the client thread. The <systemitem>report_heuristics</systemitem> argument is set
          to <literal>false</literal>, so the Transaction Service makes no reports about possible heuristic decisions.
        </para>
        <programlisting language="Java" role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/indirect_and_implicit_close.java" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" parse="text" /></programlisting>
      </example>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Transaction originator: direct and explicit</title>
      
      <example>
        <title>Direct and explicit transaction originator</title>
        <programlisting role="JAVA" language="Java"><xi:include href="extras/direct_and_explicit.java"
        xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" parse="text" /></programlisting>
        <para>
          This transaction originator uses direct context management and explicit transaction propagation. The client
          uses a factory object supporting the <interfacename>CosTransactions::TransactionFactory</interfacename>
          interface to create a new transaction, and uses the returned <classname>Control</classname> object to retrieve
          the <classname>Terminator</classname> and <classname>Coordinator</classname> objects.
        </para>
        <para>
          The client issues requests, some of which involve transactional objects. This example uses explicit
          propagation of the context. The <classname>Control</classname> object reference is passed as an explicit
          parameter of the request. It is declared in the OMG IDL of the interface.
        </para>
        <programlisting language="Java" role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/direct_and_explicit_client_requests.java" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" parse="text" /></programlisting>
        <para>
          The transaction originator uses the <classname>Terminator</classname> object to commit the transaction. The
          <systemitem>report_heuristics</systemitem> argument is set to <literal>false</literal>, so the Transaction
          Service makes no reports about possible heuristic decisions.
        </para>
        <programlisting language="Java" role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/direct_and_explicit_commit.java" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" parse="text" /></programlisting>
      </example>
    </section>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Implementing a transactional client</title>
    <para>
      The <methodname>commit</methodname> operation of <classname>Current</classname> or the
      <interfacename>Terminator</interfacename> interface takes the <type>boolean</type>
      <option>report_heuristics</option> parameter. If the <option>report_heuristics</option> argument is
      <literal>false</literal>, the commit operation can complete as soon as the <classname>Coordinator</classname>
      makes the decision to commit or roll back the transaction. The application does not need to wait for the
      <classname>Coordinator</classname> to complete the commit protocol by informing all the participants of the
      outcome of the transaction. This can significantly reduce the elapsed time for the commit operation, especially
      where participant <classname>Resource</classname> objects are located on remote network nodes. However, no
      heuristic conditions can be reported to the application in this case.
    </para>
    <para>
      Using the <option>report_heuristics</option> option guarantees that the commit operation does not complete until
      the <classname>Coordinator</classname> completes the commit protocol with all <classname>Resource</classname>
      objects involved in the transaction. This guarantees that the application is informed of any non-atomic outcomes
      of the transaction, through one of the exceptions <systemitem>HeuristicMixed</systemitem> or
      <systemitem>HeuristicHazard</systemitem>. However, it increases the application-perceived elapsed time for the
      commit operation.
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Implementing a recoverable server</title>
    <para>
      A Recoverable Server includes at least one transactional object and one resource object, each of which have
      distinct responsibilities.
    </para>
    
    <section>
      <title>Transactional object</title>
      <para>
        The transactional object implements the transactional object's operations<!--What??--> and registers a
        <classname>Resource</classname> object with the <classname>Coordinator</classname>, so that the Recoverable
        Server's resources, including any necessary recovery, can commit.
      </para>
      <para>
        The <classname>Resource</classname> object identifies the involvement of the Recoverable Server in a particular
        transaction. This requires a <classname>Resource</classname> object to only be registered in one transaction at
        a time. Register a different <classname>Resource</classname> object for each transaction in which a recoverable
        server is concurrently involved. A transactional object may receive multiple requests within the scope of a
        single transaction. It only needs to register its involvement in the transaction once. The
        <methodname>is_same_transaction</methodname> operation allows the transactional object to determine if the
        transaction associated with the request is one in which the transactional object is already registered.
      </para>
      <para>
        The <classname>hash_transaction</classname> operations allow the transactional object to reduce the number of
        transaction comparisons it has to make. All <classname>Coordinators</classname> for the same transaction return
        the same hash code. The <methodname>is_same_transaction</methodname> operation only needs to be called on
        <classname>Coordinators</classname> with the same hash code as the <classname>Coordinator</classname> of the
        current request.
      </para>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Resource object</title>
      <para>
        A <classname>Resource</classname> object participates in the completion of the transaction, updates the
        resources of the Recoverable Server in accordance with the transaction outcome, and ensures termination of the
        transaction, including across failures.
      </para>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Reliable servers</title>
      <para>
        A <firstterm>Reliable Server</firstterm> is a special case of a Recoverable Server. A Reliable Server can use
        the same interface as a Recoverable Server to ensure application integrity for objects that do not have
        recoverable state. In the case of a Reliable Server, the transactional object can register a
        <classname>Resource</classname> object that replies <systemitem>VoteReadOnly</systemitem> to
        <methodname>prepare</methodname> if its integrity constraints are satisfied. It replies
        <systemitem>VoteRollback</systemitem> if it finds a problem. This approach allows the server to apply integrity
        constraints which apply to the transaction as a whole, rather than to individual requests to the server.
      </para>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Examples</title>
      <example>
        <title>Reliable server</title>
        <programlisting role="JAVA" language="Java"><xi:include href="extras/reliable_server.java" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" parse="text" /></programlisting>
      </example>
      
      <example>
        <title>Transactional object</title>
        <programlisting role="JAVA" language="Java"><xi:include href="extras/transactional_object.java" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" parse="text" /></programlisting>
      </example>
    </section>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Failure models</title>
    <para>
      The Transaction Service provides atomic outcomes for transactions in the presence of application, system or
      communication failures. From the viewpoint of each user object role, two types of failure are relevant:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A local failure, which affects the object itself.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          An external failure, such as failure of another object or failure in the communication with an object.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      The transaction originator and transactional server handle these failures in different ways.
    </para>
    <section>
      <title>Transaction originator</title>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Local failure</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              If a Transaction originator fails before the originator issues <systemitem>commit</systemitem>, the
              transaction is rolled back. If the originator fails after issuing commit and before the outcome is
              reported, the transaction can either commit or roll back, depending on timing. In this case, the
              transaction completes without regard to the failure of the originator.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>External failure</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Any external failure which affects the transaction before the originator issues
              <systemitem>commit</systemitem> causes the transaction to roll back. The standard exception
              <systemitem>TransactionRolledBack</systemitem> is raised in the originator when it issues
              <systemitem>commit</systemitem>.
            </para>
            <para>
              If a failure occurs after commit and before the outcome is reported, the client may not be informed of the
              outcome of the transaction. This depends on the nature of the failure, and the use of the
              <option>report_heuristics</option> option of <systemitem>commit</systemitem>. For example, the transaction
              outcome is not reported to the client if communication between the client and the
              <classname>Coordinator</classname> fails.
            </para>
            <para>
              A client can determine the outcome of the transaction by using method <methodname>get_status</methodname>
              on the <classname>Coordinator</classname>. However, this is not reliable because it may return the status
              <systemitem>NoTransaction</systemitem>, which is ambiguous. The transaction could have committed and been
              forgotten, or it could have rolled back and been forgotten.
            </para>
            <para>
              An originator is only guaranteed to know the transaction outcome in one of two ways.
            </para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  if its implementation includes a <classname>Resource</classname> object, so that it can participate in
                  the two-phase commit procedure.
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  The originator and <classname>Coordinator</classname> must be located in the same failure domain.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Transactional server</title>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Local failure</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              If the Transactional Server fails, optional checks by a Transaction Service implementation may make the
              transaction to roll back. Without such checks, whether the transaction rolls back depends on whether the
              commit decision is already made, such as when an unchecked client invokes <systemitem>commit</systemitem>
              before receiving all replies from servers.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>External failure</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Any external failure affecting the transaction during the execution of a Transactional Server causes the
              transaction to be rolled back. If the failure occurs while the transactional object’s method is executing,
              the failure has no effect on the execution of this method. The method may terminate normally, returning
              the reply to its client. Eventually the <systemitem>TransactionRolledBack</systemitem> exception is
              returned to a client issuing <systemitem>commit</systemitem>.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Recoverable server</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Behavior of a recoverable server when failures occur is determined by the two phase commit protocol
              between the <classname>Coordinator</classname> and the recoverable server’s
              <classname>Resource</classname> object.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Summary</title>
    <para>
      When you develop OTS applications which use the raw OTS interfaces, be aware of the following items:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Create <classname>Resource</classname> and <classname>SubtransactionAwareResource</classname> objects for each
          object which will participate within the transaction or subtransaction. These resources handle the
          persistence, concurrency control, and recovery for the object. The OTS invokes these objects during the
          prepare, commit, and abort phases of the transaction or subtransaction, and the
          <classname>Resources</classname> then perform all appropriate work.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Register <classname>Resource</classname> and <classname>SubtransactionAwareResource</classname> objects at the
          correct time within the transaction, and ensure that the object is only registered once within a given
          transaction. As part of registration, a <classname>Resource</classname> receives a reference to a
          <classname>RecoveryCoordinator</classname>, which must be made persistent so that recovery can occur in the
          event of a failure.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          For nested transactions, make sure that any propagation of resources, such as locks to parent transactions,
          are done correctly. You also need to manage propagation of <classname>SubtransactionAwareResource</classname>
          objects to parents.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          in the event of failures, drive the crash recovery for each <classname>Resource</classname> which participates
          within the transaction.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      The OTS does not provide any <classname>Resource</classname> implementations.
    </para>
  </section>
</chapter>