<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "JBossJTS_Development_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter>
  <title>JBossTS Basics</title>
    
  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
      JBossTS is based upon the original Arjuna system developed at the University of Newcastle between 1986 and
      1995. Arjuna predates the OTS specification and includes many features not found in the OTS. JBossTS is a superset
      of the OTS. Applications written using the standard OTS interfaces are portable across OTS implementations.
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <title>JBossTS features in terms of OTS specifications</title>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          full draft 5 compliance, with support for Synchronization objects and PropagationContexts.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          support for subtransactions.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          implicit context propagation where support from the ORB is available.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          support for multi-threaded applications.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          fully distributed transaction managers, i.e., there is no central transaction manager, and the creator of a
          top-level transaction is responsible for its termination. Separate transaction manager support is also
          available, however.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          transaction interposition.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          X/Open compliance, including checked transactions. This checking can optionally be disabled. Note: checked
          transactions are disabled by default, i.e., any thread can terminate a transaction.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          JDBC support.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Full JTA 1.1 support.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      You can use JBossTS in three different levels, which correspond to the sections in this chapter, and are each
      explored in their own chapters as well.
    </para>
    <para>
      Because of differences in ORB implementations, JBossTS uses a separate ORB Portability library which acts as an
      abstraction later. Many of the examples used throughout this manual use this library. Refer to the ORB Portability
      Manual for more details.
    </para>

    
    <section>
      <title>Raw OTS</title>
      <para>
        The OTS is only a protocol engine for driving registered resources through a two-phase commit protocol. You are
        responsible for building and registering the <interfacename>Resource</interfacename> objects which handle
        persistence and concurrency control, ensuring ACID properties for transactional application objects. You need to
        register <interfacename>Resources</interfacename> at appropriate times, and ensure that a given
        <interfacename>Resource</interfacename> is only registered within a single transaction. Programming at the raw
        OTS level is extremely basic. You as the programmer are responsible for almost everything to do with
        transactions, including managing persistence and concurrency control on behalf of every transactional object.
      </para>
      
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Enhanced OTS functionality</title>
      <para>
        The OTS implementation of nested transactions is extremely limited, and can lead to the generation of heuristic
        results. An example of such a result is when a subtransaction coordinator discovers part of the way through
        committing that some resources cannot commit, but being unable to tell the committed resources to abort. JBossTS
        allows nested transactions to execute a full two-phase commit protocol, which removes the possibility that some
        resources will comment while others roll back.
      </para>
      <para>
        When resources are registered with a transaction, you have no control over the order in which these resources
        are invoked during the commit/abort protocol. For example, if previously registered resources are replaced with
        newly registered resources, resources registered with a subtransaction are merged with the subtraction's
        parent. JBossTS provides an additional Resource subtype which you this level of control.
      </para>
      
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Advanced API</title>
      <para>
        The OTS does not provide any <interfacename>Resource</interfacename> implementations. You are responsible for
        implementing these interfaces. The interfaces defined within the OTS specification are too low-level for most
        application programmers. Therefore, JBossTS includes <application>Transactional Objects for Java
        (TXOJ)</application>, which makes use of the raw Common Object Services interfaces but provides a higher-level
        API for building transactional applications and frameworks. This API automates much of the activities concerned
        with participating in an OTS transaction, freeing you to concentrate on application development, rather than
        transactions.
      </para>
      <para>
        The architecture of the system is shown in Figure 2. The API interacts with the concurrency control and
        persistence services, and automatically registers appropriate resources for transactional objects. These
        resources may also use the persistence and concurrency services.
      </para>
      <para>
        JBossTS exploits object-oriented techniques to provide you with a toolkit of Java classes which are inheritable
        by application classes, to obtain transactional properties. These classes form a hierarchy, illustrated in <xref
        linkend="jbossts-class-hierarchy" />.
      </para>
      <figure id="jbossts-class-hierarchy">
        <title>JBossTS class hierarchy</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/jbossts-class-hierarchy.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
          <textobject>
            <para>JBossTS class hierarchy</para>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>
        Your main responsibilities are specifying the scope of transactions and setting appropriate locks within
        objects. JBossTS guarantees that transactional objects will be registered with, and be driven by, the
        appropriate transactions. Crash recovery mechanisms are invoked automatically in the event of failures. When
        using the provided interfaces, you do not need to create or register <classname>Resource</classname> objects or
        call services controlling persistence or recovery.  If a transaction is nested, resources are automatically
        propagated to the transaction’s parent upon commit.
      </para>
      <para>
        The design and implementation goal of JBossTS was to provide a programming system for constructing
        fault-tolerant distributed applications. Three system properties were considered highly important:
      </para>
      <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colwidth="150px"/>
          <colspec colwidth="290px"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>Integration of Mechanisms</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  Fault-tolerant distributed systems require a variety of system functions for naming, locating and
                  invoking operations upon objects, as well as for concurrency control, error detection and recovery
                  from failures. These mechanisms are integrated in a way that is easy for you to use.
                </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Flexibility</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  Mechanisms must be flexible, permitting implementation of application-specific enhancements, such as
                  type-specific concurrency and recovery control, using system defaults.
                </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Portability</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  You need to be able to run JBossTS on any ORB.
                </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
      <para>
        JBossTS is implemented in Java and extensively uses the type-inheritance facilities provided by the language to
        provide user-defined objects with characteristics such as persistence and recoverability.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>

  
  <section>
    <title>JBossTS and the OTS implementation</title>
    <para>
      The OTS specification is written with flexibility in mind, to cope with different application requirements for
      transactions. JBossTS supports all optional parts of the OTS specification. In addition, if the specification
      allows functionality to be implemented in a variety of different ways, JBossTS supports all possible
      implementations.
    </para>
    <table>
      <title>JBossTS implementation of OTS specifications</title>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colwidth="220px"/>
        <colspec colwidth="220px"/>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>OTS specification</entry>
            <entry>JBossTS default implementation</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>
                If the transaction service chooses to restrict the availability of the transaction context, then it
                should raise the <systemitem>Unavailable</systemitem> exception.
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>
                JBossTS does not restrict the availability of the transaction context.
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>
                An implementation of the transaction service need not initialize the transaction context for every
                request.
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>
                JBossTS only initializes the transaction context if the interface supported by the target object extends
                the <interfacename>TransactionalObject</interfacename> interface.
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>
                An implementation of the transaction service may restrict the ability for the
                <classname>Coordinator</classname>, <classname>Terminator</classname>, and
                <classname>Control</classname> objects to be transmitted or used in other execution environments to
                enable it to guarantee transaction integrity.
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>
                JBossTS does not impose restrictions on the propagation of these objects.
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>
                The transaction service may restrict the termination of a transaction to the client that started it.
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>
                JBossTS allows the termination of a transaction by any client that uses the
                <interfacename>Terminator</interfacename> interface. In addition, JBossTS does not impose restrictions
                when clients use the <interfacename>Current</interfacename> interface.
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>
                A <classname>TransactionFactory</classname> is located using the
                <interfacename>FactoryFinder</interfacename> interface of the life-cycle service.
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>
                JBossTS provides multiple ways in which the <classname>TransactionFactory</classname> can be located.
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>
                A transaction service implementation may use the Event Service to report heuristic decisions.
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>
                JBossTS does not use the Event Service to report heuristic decisions.
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>
                An implementation of the transaction service does not need to support nested transactions.
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>
                JBossTS supports nested transactions.
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>
                <classname>Synchronization</classname> objects must be called whenever the transaction commits.
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>
                JBossTS allows <classname>Synchronizations</classname> to be called no matter what state the transaction
                terminates with.
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>
                A transaction service implementation is not required to support interposition.
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>
                JBossTS supports various types of interposition.
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Thread class</title>
    <para>
      JBossTS is fully multi-threaded and supports the OTS notion of allowing multiple threads to be active within a
      transaction, and for a thread to execute multiple transactions. A thread can only be active within a single
      transaction at a time, however. By default, if a thread is created within the scope of a transaction, the new
      thread is not associated with the transaction. If the thread needs to be associated with the transaction, use the
      <methodname>resume</methodname> method of either the <classname>AtomicTransaction</classname> class or the
      <classname>Current</classname> class.
    </para>
    <para>
      However, if newly created threads need to automatically inherit the transaction context of their parent, then they
      should extend the <classname>OTS_Thread</classname> class.
    </para>
    <example>
      <title>Extending the <classname>OTS_Thread</classname> class</title>
      <programlisting language="Java" role="JAVA"><xi:include href="extras/OTS_Thread.java" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" parse="text" /></programlisting>
    </example>
    <para>
      Call the <methodname>run</methodname> method of <classname>OTS_Thread</classname> at the start of the application
      thread class's <methodname>run</methodname> method. Call <methodname>terminate</methodname> before you exit the
      body of the application thread’s <methodname>run</methodname> method.
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>ORB portability issues</title>
    <para>
      Although the CORBA specification is a standard, it is written so that an ORB can be implemented in multiple
      ways. As such, writing portable client and server code can be difficult. Because JBossTS has been ported to most
      of the widely available ORBs, it includes a series of ORB Portability classes and macros. If you write your
      application using these classes, it should be mostly portable between different ORBs. These classes are described
      in the separate ORB Portability Manual.
    </para>
  </section>
</chapter>

