<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "JBossJTS_Development_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter>
  <title>Tools</title>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
      This chapter includes descriptions of JTS specific tools.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>RMIC Extensions</title>
    <para>The RMIC extensions allow stubs and tie classes to be generated for transactional RMI-IIOP
      objects. A transactional object is one which wishes to receive transactional context when one
      of its methods is invoked. Without transactional object support an RMI-IIOP object won't have
      transactional context propagated to it when its methods are invoked.</para>
    <para>The tool works in two ways: i) via the command line, ii) via ANTs RMIC compiler task.
      Examples of how to use the tool via these methods are covered in the following sections.
    </para>
    <section>
      <title>Command Line Usage</title>
      <para>As this tool delegates compilation to the Sun RMIC tool it accepts the same command line
        parameters. So for more details please see it's documentation for details
        (http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.4.2/docs/tooldocs/tools.html#rmi). The following is an example
        of how this can be used:</para>
      <para>
        <programlisting role="JAVA" language="Java">java com.arjuna.common.tools.rmictool.RMICTool &lt;parameters&gt;</programlisting>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>ANT Usage</title>
      <para>The RMICTool also acts as a plug-in for the ANT RMIC task. To use the RMICTool simply
        specify the fully qualified classname as the compiler attribute, e.g.</para>
      <example>
        <title>
          Example ANT
          <classname>rmic</classname>
          declaration
        </title>
        <programlisting language="XML" role="XML"><xi:include
          href="extras/exampleRMICDeclaration.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" parse="text" /></programlisting>
      </example>
      <para>The RMICTool JAR file must either be specified in your system classpath or it should be
        copied into the lib directory of your ANT distribution for it to be found.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>

