<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "Transactions_XTS_Administration_And_Development_Guide.ent">
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "Transactions_XTS_Programmers_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter>
  <title>About This Guide</title>
  <para>
    The XTS Development Guide explains how to add resilience to distributed business processes based on web services,
    making them reliable in the event of system or network failures. It covers installation, administration, and
    development of transactional web services.
  </para>
  <para>
    The &APPSERVER; implements Web Services
    Transactions standards using <firstterm>XTS (XML Transaction Service)</firstterm>. XTS supports development and
    deployment of transaction-aware web services. It also enables web service clients to create and manage web service
    transactions from which transactional web services can be invoked. XTS ensures that the client and web services
    achieve consistent outcomes even if the systems on which they are running crash or temporarily lose network
    connectivity.
  </para>
  <para>
    XTS is compliant with the <firstterm>WS-Coordination</firstterm>, <firstterm>WS-Atomic Transaction</firstterm>, and
    <firstterm>WS-Business Activity</firstterm> specifications. The implementation supports web services and clients
    which are based on the JaxWS standard. XTS is itself implemented using services based on JaxWS.  While this guide
    discusses many Web Services standards like SOAP and WSDL, it does not attempt to address all of their fundamental
    constructs. However, basic concepts are provided where necessary.
  </para>
  <section>
    <title>Audience</title>
    <para>
      This guide is most relevant for application developers and Web service developers who are interested in building
      applications and Web services that are transaction-aware. It is also useful for system analysts and project
      managers who are unfamiliar with transactions as they pertain to Web services.
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Prerequisites</title>
    <para>
      JBoss Transaction Service uses the Java programming language and this manual assumes that you are familiar with
      programming in Java. Additional helpful skills are outlined in <xref linkend="prereqs-list" />.
    </para>
    <itemizedlist id="prereqs-list">
      <title>Prerequisite Skills for XTS Developers</title>
      <listitem><para>A Working knowledge of Web Services, including XML, SOAP, and WSDL</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>A general understanding of transactions</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>A general understanding of WS-Coordination, WS-Atomic Transaction and WS-Business Activity
      protocols</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      This guide presents overview information for all of the above. However, to aid in understanding the Web Services
      component of JBoss Transaction Service, the WS-C<footnote><para><ulink
      url="http://download.boulder.ibm.com/ibmdl/pub/software/dw/specs/ws-tx/WS-Coordination.pdf" /></para></footnote>,
      WS-Atomic Transaction<footnote><para><ulink
      url="http://download.boulder.ibm.com/ibmdl/pub/software/dw/specs/ws-tx/WS-AtomicTransaction.pdf"
      /></para></footnote>, and WS-Business Activity<footnote><para><ulink
      url="http://download.boulder.ibm.com/ibmdl/pub/software/dw/specs/ws-tx/WS-BusinessActivity.pdf"
      /></para></footnote> specifications are discussed in great detail.
    </para>
  </section>
</chapter>

